Data Structures

1)Let LASTPOST, LASTIN and LASTPRE denote the last vertex visited in a postorder, inorder and preorder traversal. Respectively, of a complete binary tree. Which of the following is always true? 
	a)LASTIN = LASTPOST
	b)LASTIN = LASTPRE
	c)LASTPRE = LASTPOST
	d)None of the above
Ans:d

2)The inorder and preorder traversal of a binary tree are d b e a f c g and a b d e c f g, respectively. The postorder traversal of the binary tree is:
	a)d e b f g c a
	b)e d b g f c a
	c)e d b f g c a
	d)d e f g b c a
Ans:a


3)Minimum number of queues to implement stack is ___________
a) 3
b) 4
c) 1
d) 2
Ans:d


4)What is the space complexity for deleting a linked list?
a) O(1)
b) O(n)
c) Either O(1) or O(n)
d) O(logn)n – 1
Ans:a

5)What is the functionality of the following code?
public void function(Node node)
{
	if(size == 0)
		head = node;
	else
	{
		Node temp,cur;
		for(cur = head; (temp = cur.getNext())!=null; cur = temp);
		cur.setNext(node);
	}
	size++;
}
a) Inserting a node at the beginning of the list
b) Deleting a node at the beginning of the list
c) Inserting a node at the end of the list
d) Deleting a node at the end of the list
Ans:c

6)You are given pointers to first and last nodes of a singly linked list, which of the following operations are dependent on the length of the linked list?
	a)Delete the first element
	b)Insert a new element as a first element
	c)Delete the last element of the list
	d)Add a new element at the end of the list
Ans:c

7) What is the functionality of the following piece of code?

public int function()
{
	Node temp = tail.getPrev();
	tail.setPrev(temp.getPrev());
	temp.getPrev().setNext(tail);
	size--;
	return temp.getItem();
}
a) Return the element at the tail of the list but do not remove it
b) Return the element at the tail of the list and remove it from the list
c) Return the last but one element from the list but do not remove it
d) Return the last but one element at the tail of the list and remove it from the list
Ans:b

8)Which one of the following is false?
a) Heap sort is an in-place algorithm
b) Heap sort has O(nlogn) average case time complexity
c) Heap sort is stable sort
d) Heap sort is a comparison-based sorting algorithm
Ans:c

9)What is the value of following recurrence. T(n) = 5T(n/5) + sqrt{n}, T(1) = 1, T(0) = 0
	a)Theta (n)
	b)Theta (n/2)
	c)Theta (n*n)
	d)Theta (nLogn)
Ans:a

10)Worst case time complexity for quick sort algorithm is
a)n^2
b)nlogn
c)n
d)(n^2)logn
Ans:a

11)Garbage Collection can be implemented by which data structure?
a)Queue
b)Stack
c)Graph
d)BST
Ans:c

12)Which one of the following is an application of Stack Data Structure?
	a)Managing function calls
	b)The stock span problem
	c)Arithmetic expression evaluation
	d)All of the above
Ans:d

13)The following postfix expression with single digit operands is evaluated using a stack:
              8 2 3 ^ / 2 3 * + 5 1 * - 
Note that ^ is the exponentiation operator. The top two elements of the stack after the first * is evaluated are:
	a)6,1
	b)5,7
	c)3,2
	d)1,5
Ans:b

14)Which data structure is used for undo-redo operation and how many ?
a)Stack,2
b)Queue,2
c)Stack,1
d)Queue,1
Ans:a

15)To evaluate an expression without any embedded function calls:
	a)One stack is enough
	b)Two stacks are needed
	c)As many stacks as the height of the expression tree are needed
	d)A Turing machine is needed in the general case
Ans:a

16)Which of the following is not an inherent application of stack?
	a)Implementation of recursion
	b)Evaluation of a postfix expression
	c)Job scheduling
	d)Reverse a string
Ans:c

17)A Priority-Queue is implemented as a Max-Heap. Initially, it has 5 elements. The level-order traversal of the heap is given below: 10, 8, 5, 3, 2 Two new elements ”1‘ and ”7‘ are inserted in the heap in that order. The level-order traversal of the heap after the insertion of the elements is:
	a)10, 8, 7, 5, 3, 2, 1
	b)10, 8, 7, 2, 3, 1, 5
	c)10, 8, 7, 1, 2, 3, 5
	d)10, 8, 7, 3, 2, 1, 5
Ans:d

18)Which of the following option is not correct?
	a)If the queue is implemented with a linked list, keeping track of a front pointer, Only rear pointer s will change during an insertion into an non-empty queue.
	b)Queue data structure can be used to implement least recently used (LRU) page fault algorithm and Quick short algorithm.
	c)Queue data structure can be used to implement Quick short algorithm but not least recently used (LRU) page fault algorithm.
	d)Both (A) and (C)
Ans:c

19) If a problem can be solved by combining optimal solutions to non-overlapping problems, the strategy is called _____________
a) Dynamic programming
b) Greedy
c) Divide and conquer
d) Recursion
Ans:c

20)Which one of the following is used to define the structure of the relation, deleting relations and relating schemas?
a) DML(Data Manipulation Langauge)
b) DDL(Data Definition Langauge)
c) Query
d) Relational Schema
Ans:b

21)Heap allocation is required for languages that
	a)use dynamic scope rules
	b)support dynamic data structures
	c)support recursion
	d)support recursion and dynamic data structures					
Ans:b

22)Array implementation of Stack is not dynamic, which of the following statements supports this argument?
a) space allocation for array is fixed and cannot be changed during run-time
b) user unable to give the input for stack operations
c) a runtime exception halts execution
d) improper program compilation
Ans:a

23)The basic data type char(n) is a _____ length character string and varchar(n) is _____ length character.
a) Fixed, equal
b) Equal, variable
c) Fixed, variable
d) Variable, equal
Ans:c

24)Consider a directed graph with n vertices and m edges such that all edges have same edge weights. Find the complexity of the best known algorithm to compute the minimum spanning tree of the graph?
	a)O(m+n)
	b)O(m logn)
	c)O(mn)
	d)O(n logm)
Ans:a

25)If we want to search any name in the phone directory , which is the most efficient data structure?
	a)Binary search Tree
	b)Balanced BST
	c)Trie
	d)Linked list
Ans:c

26)Which kind of traversal order trie gives the lexicographical sorting of the set of the strings?
	a)Preorder
	b)Postorder
	c)Level order
	d)Inorder
Ans:a

27)Consider a situation where swap operation is very costly. Which of the following sorting algorithms should be preferred so that the number of swap operations are minimized in general?
	a)Heap Sort
	b)Selection Sort
	c)Insertion Sort
	d)Merge Sort
Ans:b

28)Suppose we are sorting an array of eight integers using heapsort, and we have just finished some heapify (either maxheapify or minheapify) operations. The array now looks like this: 16 14 15 10 12 27 28 How many heapify operations have been performed on root of heap?
	a)1
	b)2
	c)3 or 4
	d)5 or 6
Ans:b

29)Which sorting algorithm will take least time when all elements of input array are identical? Consider typical implementations of sorting algorithms.
	a)Insertion Sort
	b)Heap Sort
	c)Merge Sort
	d)Selection Sort
Ans:a

30)Time Complexity of DFS is? (V – number of vertices, E – number of edges)
a) O(V + E)
b) O(V)
c) O(E)
d) O(V*E)

Ans:a